Why are resume sections important?
Resume sections are important because they allow you to showcase your skills, education and professional experience in a way that makes sense to potential employers. Using standard resume sections lets you present your professional highlights in a format that hiring teams can use to determine your ranking as a candidate.

One of the most common elements across all resumes is a professional header. This section includes your name, which you might format as the page's title so employers can identify your resume among those of other candidates. You may also include a phone number and email address, ensuring you provide contact information that employers can use to easily ask you questions or schedule interviews. Try using an email address with a professional handle.

Depending on the type of job you're applying for, you might include a link to an online portfolio or your profile on a professional networking site. 

A resume summary briefly explains your professional history and mentions key skills, education or work experience that make you a desirable candidate. Consider reviewing the job posting to see the traits employers prefer. Try to describe yourself in a way that not only appeals to hiring managers but also accurately reflects your skills and the rest of your resume. An example of a professional summary is:
Professional Summary
Thoughtful construction laborer with more than five years of experience helping manage teams toward successful and safe completion of housing projects.

Many employers set minimum education requirements for certain positions. You can assure hiring managers that you meet these by including an education section. Consider listing educational experiences in reverse chronological order and in relation to where you are in your career. For instance, a recent college graduate may feature their education and include more details because that's the bulk of their experience. Someone who's been in the workforce would have a smaller, less detailed education section after their relevant work experience.
Each entry in the education section typically contains the name of the degree and the awarding institution. Depending on the job you're applying for and where you are in your career, you might also include:
The school's location
Your minor
Your graduation year (if you graduated within the past three years)
Your GPA, if it was above 3.4.
Any relevant honors or academic recognition, coursework, activities or other achievements obtained during your education

The work experience section of your resume showcases the work you've completed in previous roles. List your most relevant work history, beginning with your most recent job, focusing on your experiences from the last 10 to 15 years. For example, if you've been working as a marketer for 11 years, you can exclude jobs from earlier in your life that may not be relevant to the position you're currently seeking. Alternatively, if you have little professional experience, you can list unrelated employment history to demonstrate your work ethic and transferable skills.

When describing your experience, focus on the results you achieved and the skills you used to do so. Simply listing a bulleted job description misses the opportunity to highlight your expertise and talent. Make every word work for you and balance the resume with white space. Save the details for the cover letter.

Each entry in the work experience section contains the job title, employment dates, employer name and location. You may also include a few bullet points describing relevant duties and accomplishments and use the past tense when describing past roles. Consider using action verbs and metrics to quantify your achievements. 
While your education and work experience highlight skills you've learned throughout your career, you can call out these traits in a designated section. Consider including relevant hard and soft skills, tools and software you're proficient with. As you read through job posts, try writing down keywords that match your skills and include them in this section as appropriate.

Some employers require certifications, especially if you work in a highly regulated field like engineering, construction or food service. Consider creating a separate certifications section to highlight relevant qualifications. You can include the official name of the certification and the awarding institution. Additionally, you might add the year you earned the certification or its expiration year.

The last section to consider adding to your resume is a short list of other relevant accomplishments. Examples include volunteer work, community awards and memberships in professional associations. These entries may demonstrate your work ethic, commitment to your community and ability to pursue continuing education in your field. Focus on activities that relate to the job description, though unrelated activities may demonstrate transferable skills.